New Zealand Institute for Language, Brain and Behaviour University of Canterbury, New Zealand

james.brand@canterbury.ac.nz
https://jamesbrandscience.github.io

Research Focus

How do cognitive biases shape our language? My research focuses on the different ways that human language has been shaped by the brain. My approach to raising and answering research questions on this topic is highly multidisciplinary, with the aim being to reach a synthesis between experimental psychology, corpus linguistics and computational cognition. In doing so, I hope to progress our empirical and theoretical understanding of questions concerning how languages are learnt, processed and subsequently evolve.

Academic Appointments

| Oct, 2018 - Present | Post-doctoral Research Fellow (Marsden Fund) University of Canterbury PIs: Dr. Kevin Watson, Prof. Jen Hay & Dr. Lynn Clark Project: Towards an improved theory of language change: understanding the covariation of linguistic variables within and across speakers |
|---------------------------|--|
| June, 2017 - Sept 2018 | Post-doctoral Research Associate (Leverhulme Trust) Lancaster University PIs: Dr. Dermot Lynott & Prof. Louise Connell Project: Emergent categorical structure in the human conceptual system |
| Feв, 2017 - June, 2017 | Research Assistant Lancaster University PI: Dr. Michelle To Project: Influence of anxiety on body perception for underweight and overweight individuals |
| DEC, 2016 - June, 2017 | Research Assistant (ESRC) Lancaster University PI: Prof. Padraic Monaghan Project: Investigating the role of multiple cues in word learning |

Education

| Enrolled, 2020 | Certificate of Proficiency in Te Reo Māori (TREO110) Univeristy of Canterbury |
|----------------|---|
| June, 2017 | Ph.D. Psychology Lancaster University |
| | Title: The Role of Cognitive Factors on the Development and Evolution of the Vocabulary |
| | Supervisors: Prof. Padraic Monaghan & Dr. Peter Walker |
| Nov, 2012 | M.Sc. Evolution of Language and Cognition University of Edinburgh |
| June, 2010 | B.A. English Language Sheffield Hallam University |
| March, 2010 | CertTESOL (Certificate in Teaching English to Speakers of Other Languages) Trinity College London |

Publications

Brand, J., Hay, J., Clark, L., Watson, K., & Sóskuthy, M. (*to be submitted, Feb 2020*). At the margins of vowel-space change: Leaders and laggers in the evolution of vocalic subsystems. *Journal of Phonetics*. Supplementary material available from: https://tinyurl.com/brandetal2020suppl

Chines and letters / /timesel and /length detalesses him.

Shiny app: https://tinyurl.com/brandetal2020shiny

- Brand, J., Hay, J., Clark, L., Watson, K., & Sóskuthy, M. (2019). Systematic covariation of monophthongs across speakers of New Zealand English. In Calhoun, S., Escudero, P., Tabain, M., & Warren, P. (eds.) *Proceedings of the 19th International Congress of Phonetic Sciences, Melbourne, Australia 2019* (pp. 1878-1881). https://tinyurl.com/brandetal2019
- Sóskuthy, M., Hay, J., & **Brand, J.** (2019). Horizontal diphthong shift in New Zealand English. In Calhoun, S., Escudero, P., Tabain, M., & Warren, P. (eds.) *Proceedings of the 19th International Congress of Phonetic Sciences, Melbourne, Australia 2019* (pp. 597-601). https://tinyurl.com/soskuthyetal2019 award winning

 Repository: https://osf.io/74mza
- Lynott, D., Connell, L., Brysbaert, M., **Brand, J.,** & Carney, J. (2019). The Lancaster Sensorimotor Norms: multidimensional measures of perceptual and action strength for 40,000 English words. *Behavior Research Methods*, 1-21. https://tinyurl.com/lynottetal2019
 Repository: https://osf.io/7emr6/
- **Brand, J.,** Monaghan, P., & Walker, P. (2018). Changing signs: Testing how sound-symbolism supports early word learning. *Proceedings of the 40th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society* (pp. 1396-1401). https://tinyurl.com/brandetal2018
- **Brand, J.,** Monaghan, P., & Walker, P. (2017). The changing role of form-to-meaning mappings for the growing vocabulary. *Cognitive Science*. doi:10.1111/cogs.12565. https://tinyurl.com/brandetal2017 Repository: https://tinyurl.com/brandetal2017repo
- Monaghan, P., **Brand**, J., Frost, R.L.A., & Taylor, G. (2017). Multiple, noisy cues for word learning results in robust, generalisable learning. *Proceedings of the 39th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society* (pp. 817-822). https://tinyurl.com/monghanetal2017

Talks & Presentations

- **Brand, J.,** Hay, J., Clark, L., Watson, K., & Sóskuthy, M. (2020). At the margins of vowel-space change: Leaders and laggers in the evolution of vocalic subsystems. *Talk to be presented at the 17th biennial conference of the Association for Laboratory Phonology*, Vancouver, CA. 5% acceptance rate
- CCC [Gnevsheva, K., Grama, J., Diskin, C., Hay, J., Foulkes, P., Drager, K., Travis, C., Gonzalez, S., Loakes, D., Sheard, E., Docherty, G., & Brand, J.]. (2020). Sound change in word classes and individual words in Australian and New Zealand English. *Paper to be presented at the Colloquium of the British Association of Academic Phoneticians (BAAP)*, York, UK.
- CCC [Grama, J., Gnevsheva, K., Hay, J., Brand, J., Gonzalez, S., Loakes, D., Docherty, G., Sheard, E., Foulkes, P., Diskin, C., Drager, K. & Travis, C.] (2019) Just a word: Sound change at the level of the word across dialects. *Talk presented at the Australian Linguistic Society conference*, Sydney, AU.

CCC [Diskin, C., Hay, J., Drager, K., Foulkes, P., Gnevsheva, K., Grama, J. Brand, J., Travis, C., Loakes, D., Docherty, G., Walker, J. Sheard, E. & Gonzalez, S.] (2019) The emergence of the discourse-pragmatic marker 'just': linking changes in usage to changes in pronunciation. *Talk presented at the Linguistic Society of New Zealand conference*, Christchurch NZ.

- CCC [Gnevsheva, K., Grama, J., Hay, J., Drager, K., Foulkes, P., **Brand, J.**, Gonzalez, S., Travis, C., Sheard, E., Loakes, D., Docherty, G., & Diskin, C.] (2019). Just a word: Lexeme-specific sound changes. *Talk presented at the Linguistic Society of New Zealand conference*, Christchurch NZ.
- Sóskuthy, M., Hay, J., & **Brand**, **J.** (2019). Horizontal diphthong shift in New Zealand English. *Talk presented at the 40th International Congress of the Phonetic Sciences*, Melbourne AU. https://osf.io/nhsek/award winning
- **Brand, J.,** Hay, J., Clark, L., Watson, K., & Sóskuthy, M. (2019). Systematic covariation of monophthongs across speakers of New Zealand English. *Talk presented at the 40th International Congress of the Phonetic Sciences*, Melbourne AU. https://tinyurl.com/brandetalICPhS
- **Brand, J.** (2018). Predicting the age of acquisition of concepts from sensorimotor experience. *Talk presented at the 4th Language and Communicative Development Conference (LuCiD)*, Manchester UK. https://tinyurl.com/brandLuCiD award winning
- **Brand, J.,** & Monaghan, P. (2018). Experimental diachronics: Predictors of lexical stability and change in language evolution. *Talk presented at the* 12th *Summer School of Linguistics*, Kroměříž CZ https://tinyurl.com/brandSSoL
- **Brand, J.,** Monaghan, P., & Walker, P. (2018). Changing signs: Testing how sound-symbolism supports early word learning. *Poster presented at the 40th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*, Madison US.
- Monaghan, P., **Brand**, J., Frost, R.L.A., & Taylor, G. (2017). Multiple, noisy cues for word learning results in robust, generalisable learning. *Talk presented at the 39th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*, London UK.

Ph.D. Thesis

Brand, J., (2017). The Role of Cognitive Factors on the Development and Evolution of the Vocabulary. *Doctoral dissertation, Lancaster University*. https://tinyurl.com/brandPhD

Tutorials and Online Resources

Interactive web app for exploring Lancaster Sensorimotor Norms

https://tinyurl.com/SMnorms

Vowel plot animations

https://tinyurl.com/vowelanimation

Introduction to open science practices

https://tinyurl.com/opensciprac

GitHub for beginners

https://tinyurl.com/githubbegin

Data exploration and visualisation in R

https://tinyurl.com/datavisR

Artificial language learning and PyschoPy

https://tinyurl.com/artificallang

Student Supervision

2020 - **Jacq Jones** (Associate supervisor) present Mixed Signals: Language Use and

Mixed Signals: Language Use and Nonbinary Gender Identities Ph.D. candidate (Linguistics, University of Canterbury)

Reviewing Service

| Journals | Conference proceedings |
|--------------------------------|---|
| Journal of Memory and Language | Cognitive Science Society |
| Behaviour Research Methods | Embodied and Situated Language Processing |
| PLoS ONE | Laboratory Phonology |
| Cognitive Development | Evolution of Language |

Honours and Awards

| 2019 | International Congress of the Phonetic Sciences Best Early Career Researcher paper |
|-------------|--|
| 2018 | Language and Communicative Development Conference (LuCiD) Best Early Career Researcher paper |
| 2016 | Experimental Psychology Society Grindley Grant for International Conference Attendance: £500 |
| 2015 | Experimental Psychology Society Grindley Grant for UK Conference Attendance: £500 |
| 2013 - 2016 | Lancaster University Departmental Studentship: £14,000 annual stipend with fee waiver |

Teaching

| 2020 | Ling310: Linguistic Research and New Zealand English Lecturer and Tutor (Linguistics, University of Canterbury) |
|-------------|---|
| 2018 | 12 th Summer School of Linguistics Invited Lecturer (Kroměříž CZ) |
| 2016 - 2017 | Personal Statistics Tutor Undergraduate Psychology Statistics |
| 2015; 2016 | M.Sc. Analysing and Interpreting Psychological Data Teaching Assistant (Psychology, Lancaster University) |
| 2015; 2016 | 2 nd Year Undergraduate Statistics Teaching Assistant (Psychology, Lancaster University) |
| 2015 | 2 nd Year Understanding Neuropsychology Guest Lecturer (Psychology, Lancaster University) |
| 2015 | 2 nd Year Undergraduate Statistics Surgery Tutor (Psychology, Lancaster University) |
| 2014; 2016 | 2 nd Year Undergraduate Cognitive Psychology Seminar Tutor (Psychology, Lancaster University) |
| 2014 | 1 st Year Undergraduate Statistics Surgery Tutor (Psychology, Lancaster University) |
| 2013; 2014 | 1 st Year Undergraduate Psychological Approaches Teaching Assistant (Psychology, Lancaster University) |
| | |

Organised Workshops

| 2020 | Word-specific phenomena in the realization of vowel categories: Methodological and theoretical perspectives https://tinyurl.com/labphon2020CCC LabPhon 17 Satellite Workshop, Vancouver CA |
|------|--|
| 2019 | Open Science Practices for Linguists https://tinyurl.com/NZLSworkshop New Zealand Linguistics Society, University of Canterbury NZ |
| 2019 | Data Visualisation with R https://tinyurl.com/data-vis Language Data Analysis Summer School, University of Canterbury NZ |
| 2018 | Artificial Language Learning and PsychoPy https://tinyurl.com/artificallang Summer School of Linguistics, Kroměříž CZ |
| 2017 | Using Amazon's Mechanical Turk for Data Collection https://tinyurl.com/AMTurk New Tricks, Lancaster University UK |

Professional Activities

| 2019 - present | NZILBB seminar series Organiser |
|-------------------|--|
| 2019 | New Zealand Linguistics Society conference (NZLS) Programme Committee Member |
| 2018 | Embodied and Situated Language Processing conference (ESLP) Programme Committee Member |
| 2018 | em.path (AHRC and University of the West of England) Round Table Member |
| 2017 | 23 rd Architectures and Mechanisms of Language Processing conference (AMLaP) Conference Committee Member |
| 2016 | 5 th Implicit Learning Seminar Conference Committee Member |
| 2014 - 2016 | ESRC International Centre for Language and Communicative Development Knowledge Exchange and Training Committee |
| 2014 - 2015 | Internal Seminar Series Organiser Department of Psychology, Lancaster University |

Science Communication and Outreach

| May, 2015; | Presenter at LuCiD and Lancaster BabyLab Campus in the City |
|-------------|---|
| 2016 | Lancaster, UK |
| Nov, 2015 | Presenter at 'Kids say the funniest things' at the ESRC Festival of Social Sciences Manchester Museum, UK |
| - | |
| July, 2015 | Supervisor for South Lakes Federation Poster competition Lancaster University |
| June, 2013; | Presenter at Lancaster University UCAS (Universities and Colleges Admissions Service) |
| 2014 | open day |
| | open day Lancaster University |

Computing Proficiency

Highly proficient in **R** Highly proficient in programming in **E-Prime**

Highly proficient in SPSS Highly Proficient in programming in PsychoPy

Highly proficient in **Shiny** Highly Proficient in programming in **OpenSesame**

Highly proficient in **Audacity** Highly proficient in using **Qualtrics**

Highly proficient in LaTeX Highly proficient in Microsoft Office applications

Familiar with **Python** Familiar with **Praat**

Familiar with **jsPsych** Familiar with **psiTurk**

Affiliations

New Zealand Institute for Language, Brain and Behaviour (NZILBB)

Canberra Corpus Collective

PrOSPr (Promoting Open Science Practices)

Embodied Cognition Lab

ESRC International Centre for Language and Communicative Development (LuCiD)

Language and Communication Lab

Cognitive Science Society

References

Prof. Jen HayDr. Dermot LynottProf. Padraic MonaghanNZILBBDepartment of PsychologyDepartment of PsychologyUniversity of CanterburyLancaster UniversityLancaster UniversityChristchurchLancasterLancaster

8140 LA1 4YF LA1 4YF
NZ UK UK

jen.hay@cantebury.ac.nz d.lynott@lancaster.ac.uk p.monaghan@lancaster.ac.uk